Oliver Diamond

I am a full-stack (mostly JS: React & Node) software developer with a eclectic career. Experienced in approaches that emphasise microservices, devops, CI/CD, good code design, and focussing developers on business value.

- · Current Position: Senior Engineer, Sky
- Specialisms: Node, React, Mongo, Microservices
- Passions: Linux, training juniors, functional programming, devops, Spacemacs.
- Physics, 2:1 Imperial College London (specialism: Computational Simulations)
- Extensive experience outside programming: Finance, Politics, Media, Communications

Background

I feel like I have always been a programmer: I learned PHP at age 12 to make web games with friends; and I spent 2 years building a bio-ecosystem simulator for university whilst most of my fellow students built real-world experiments.

I was not always a professional engineer though: I have worked in **politics, film production, TV & theatre development, and finance**. But I pushed and built tech solutions in all of these industries: from simple web apps, to finance & news analysis engines.

Currently I work for Sky and (most recently) for TES (formerly the Times Education Supplement) and HSBC. I've worked predominantly with the latest Javascript technologies, pushing the following philosophies: **small iterations**, microservices architectures, devops, agile, continuous delivery, constant retrospection and programmer anarchy, whilst always focussing on releasing value to clients.

In my personal life, I have been building a Kubernetes lab in my attic, **creating a Node.js focussed CI/CD plaform creation tool**, to allow for easy deployment and maintenance of home-made applications onto a home server.

Skills

Programming:

- JavaScript (Latest ES, Node, React, Express, Selenium) 7+ yrs
- Clojure (Compojure) 1+ yrs
- Java (Android, Spring) 2+ yrs
- Ruby (Rails), Python (Django)
- C++
- CSS, SCSS, Webpack, Babel
- DB (MySQL, PostgreSQL, Mongo)

Delivery/Ops:

- Microservices (Kubernetes, Docker, RabbitMQ)
- Continuous Delivery (Jenkins)
- Version control (Git, RTC)
- Linux (Ubuntu, Redhat, Debian)
- Networking (DNS, TCP/IP, HTTPS)
- Spacemacs (Emacs + Vim), Eclipse, Intellij, Android Studio

Methodologies:

- Agile (Scrum, Kanban, programmer anarchy, lots of retrospecting)
- Devops (CI/CD)
- Test Driven Development
- Behaviour Driven Development
- Pair Programming
- Microservice Architectures

Other Expertise

Government: I have 8 years experience across Government, public policy, and the digital & creative industries. I became leader of a Minister's Parliamentary Office, and I continue to support a political network that I helped to found.

Finance: Aside from my tech work in HSBC's FX dept, I have worked as an analyst at CQS Asset Management (credit-trading hedge fund) and NSBO (Chinese event-driven brokerage and corporate finance boutique).

Communications: I have worked on public policy campaigns, in political comms, and in film & theatre marketing. I have written articles for national newspapers, press releases for Government Ministers, and organised political conferences.

Work History

Sky (May 2018 - Present) | SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Our team develops and maintains a suite of services that allow Sky's Editors to generate live content and then serve it to ~6 million Set-Top-Boxes across the UK, Ireland, Germany, and Italy. As the team's Senior Engineer, I am responsible for directing the dev team's efforts; I prompt choices in technology, practices, and methodologies, aiming to facilitate my colleagues' work. As one of the only full-stack teams in Sky, we have concerns from host infrastructures to client browsers. I have also focussed on mentoring the junior and beginner developers across Sky – aiding in career progression and basic programming; leading workshops on everything from clean code, new technologies, and new methodologies.

Tes Engineering (Oct 2017 - May 2018) | SOFTWARE ENGINEER

An old company (>100 years), Tes provide teaching resources and solutions. The company converted to microservices, with (mostly) a MERN stack (MongoDB, Express, React, Node), all Dockerised and running on AWS. We embrace continuous delivery, agile, devops, open-source, programmer anarchy, tiny teams (2-4), remote first, frequent retrospection, hackdays, and a focus on team building and the education of junior developers.

HSBC GFX (Dec 2016 - Sept 2017) | DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

My team of 6 delivered a suite of microservices in Clojure and ES6 and patched them into a legacy Java 6 / dojo.js monolith. We worked from within the modern foriegn-exchange department of the investment bank, bringing their products into HSBCnet: one of the world's most used commercial payment platforms, developed on a quarterly release cycle, with manual testing, and old SDLCs.

Makers Academy (May 2016 - Sept 2017) | SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONSULTANT

London's top dev bootcamp. I was involved from the beginning in Makers Academy's consultancy arm which aimed to take freshly trained junior devs and place them in teams with Makers Academy corportate partners. True to the MA spirit, I also completed the Makers Academy course - a bootcamp focusing on professional programming best practices (Agile, TDD, BDD, Pair Programming and the philosphies of Sandi Metz, Robert C Martin & Fred George).

Bob & Co (Nov 2014 - May 2016) | HEAD OF DIGITAL AND COMMUNICATIONS

A small media (film, TV, theatre) developer, and financier. I ran the technological, research & communication efforts. I also built (and maintained) the company website (single-handed), and other applications (Java & JS) for their partners & subsidiaries. I later became Acting Director of Operations during a staff maternity leave, tasked with extensive audit and efficiency efforts in the IT, telecoms, and other office admin budgets.

SUMS Film & Media (Aug 2015 - Dec 2015) | DIGITAL CONSULTANT

An independent film producer. I directly advised the Chief Executive on their projects' digital strategies (see IMDB \leftarrow I'm three clicks from Tom Cruise :-P). I worked on various applications, including marketing websites (*PHP*).

North Square Blue Oak (Jan 2014 - Mar 2014) | ANALYST

A brokerage and corporate finance boutique, assessing new opportunities in the digital and media sectors. The company drew heavily on my technological expertise in assessing potential investments.

CQS Asset Management (Feb 2013 - Mar 2013) | *MARGINS DEPT ANALYST & SOFTWARE DEVELOPER* A \$13bn credit hedge fund: I worked in liability management analysis with collateral specialists (creating an app to assess marginal risks); and also with the strategic IT team, developing a credit price monitoring application (C#).

Office of the Digital & Cultural Minister (Nov 2008 - Nov 2014) | SENIOR PARLIAMENTARY ADVISOR I managed the Parliamentary Office of Rt. Hon. Ed Vaizey MP from the date of his Ministerial appointment. I oversaw the running of the office, interviewing, training and managing all junior staff. I worked on campaigns such as improving Wifi provision in public libraries and bringing coding into the national curriculum.

Education

Physics 2:1 (BSc & ARCS): Imperial College London (Oct 2005 - July 2008)

I focussed on computational simulations, astrophysics, plasma physics, and the practicalities of nuclear fusion energy as a future energy source.

Final Year Degree Project (C++)

I received 93% for an computer simulation investigation into the process of evolution. I wrote the program from scratch, modelling biological systems. I was praised particularly for analysing great amounts of data, spotting patterns and anomalies, presenting them accessibly and quantifying the results in a manner that the department had never seen before.

Other Interests

CACIN - The Political Creative Industries Network (2008 - 2017) | DIRECTOR

I developed and maintained relationships with many key players in the tech & creative sectors on behalf Damian Collins MP, the Rt Hon Minister Ed Vaizey MP, and the Conservative Party HQ. I ran regular panels, drinks receptions and conferences across the UK, focusing on issues from the digital single market to diversity in the media.

The Digital Bazaar, Tate South Lambeth Library (2009 – 2013) | *FOUNDING VOLUNTEER & IT EXPERT* Taught basic computer skills, smartphone, and other technology use to struggling members of the Lambeth community (many of whom did not have English as a first language). Runners-up for the CILIP Libraries Change Lives Award 2012.

Music - I have an intensely musical education. A music scholarship took me through secondary school. I sang in Christ Church Cathedral Choir, Oxford (we sang the credits to Blackadder and Vicar of Dibley; we performed in front of HM the queen; and we toured the USA, Japan, Germany, France, and Brazil). I also played the Saxophone, Violin, Piano, and quitar.

Cooking - I love cooking and spend a great deal of time in the kitchen. I have been paid to cook at events. And my recipes are popular on Instagram.

Tennis - I play regularly with a variety of partners and am coached professionally.